When I was lying there in the VA haspital,
当我销在军人医院
with a big hole blown through the middle of my life,
肢体残缺寸步难行
I started having these dreams of flying.
我开始梦见飞行
l was free.
我自由了
Sooner or later, though, you always have to wake up.
可是总有一天你会从梦中醒来
In eryo, you don't dream at all.
人在低温睡眠不会做梦
lt doesn't feel like six years.
怎会像六年
More like a fifth of tequila and an ass-kicking.
项多像宿醉并被殴打
Tommy was the scientist, not me.
汤米是科学家，我不是
He was the one whe wanted te get shot light-years out in space
他想到外层空间宇宙寻求答案
to find the answers.
为地球人寻找未来的归宿
Are we there yet?
我们到了吗?
Yeah, we're there, sunshine.
是的，我们到了，伙计
We're there.
我们到了
it's about your brother.
这是为了你兄弟
So, a week before Tommy's gonna ship out,
一周前汤米准备出发
a guy with a gun ends his journey for the paper in his wallet.
一名歹徒杀死了他，为了抢走他的钱包
You've been in cryo for five years, nine months and 22 days.
你已经低温冷藏了5年9个月22天
You will be hungry. You will be weak.
你会感到饥俄，浑身无力
If you feel nausea, please use the sacks...
如果你感到恶心，请使用呕吐袋
Me, I'm just another dumb grunt going someplace he's gonna regret.
而我只是个去错地方的春前海军陆战队员
Up ahead was Pandora.
前面就是潘多拉星球
You grew up hearing about it, but never figured I'd be going there.
我早就听说过，但是从没想过会去那里
Your brother represented a significant investment.
你的兄弟关系到一项重大投资
We'd like to talk to you about taking over his contract.
我们希望你继续完成他的合约
And since your genome is identical to his, you could step into his shoes,
由于你们基因相同，你可继承他的衣钵
so to speak.
至少我们这么认为
lt'd be a fresh start on a new world.
在新世界重新开始
And the pay is goed.
我们不会亏待你
Very good.
好极了
-Exo-packs on! Let's go! Exo-packs on! -Exo-packs on! Let's go!
-戴上氧气重，快点，戴上氧气唱 -戴上氧气重，快点
Remember, people, you lose that mask,
别忘了，伙计们，一旦失去氧气唱
you're unconscious in 20 seconds, you're dead in four minutes!
你们将在20秒名内休克4分外内死亡
Let's nobody be dead today! Looks very bad on my report.
希望今天不要出那种事 那会影响我的声誉
Hell's Gate tower, this is TAV 1-6 on approach.
塔台，16号航天飞机将降落
Crossing outer marker. Mine is in sight.
我已飞过界标，看到矿山
One life ends,
一个生命结束
another begins.
另一个生命开始
Harnesses off! Get your packs!
解开降落伞，带好背包
-Put it together, let's go! Let's go! -Harnesses off! One minute!
- 解开降落伞，快点 - 给你们一分名时间
When that ramp comes down, go directly into the base. Do not stop!
快点，舱门打开后马上下飞机，不要停留
Go straight inside. Wait for my mark!
直走里面等候我的指令
Go, go, go, go! Get out of there! Keep moving! Let's go, let's go!
快，快，快，马上下飞机
There's no such thing as an ex-Marine.
没有所谓的前海军军人
You may be out, but you never lose the attitude.
人可以退役，但精神不会退役
l told myself l could pass any test a man could pass.
我对自己说 没有什么困难是不可以战胜的
They can fix a spinal, if you got the money,
如果你有钱，医生就能让你康复
but not on vet benefits, not in this economy.
但是只靠抚恤金，根本不可能做到
Let's go, special case! Do not make me wait for you!
快点，特殊人物，别让大伙等你一个人
Well, well, ladies.
瞧瞧你们
Look at all this fresh meat!
看这群新猪肉 !
Back on Earth, these guys were Army dogs, Marines,
在地球上，他们只是为了
fighting for freedom.
自由而战的普通士兵和海军
Look out, hot rod!
当心点，笨蛋
But out here they're just hired guns,
可是在这里他们成了雇佣军
taking the money, working for the company.
为了钱给大公司卖命
Check this out, man.
你看那家伙
Meals on wheels.
坐轮椅的
Oh, man, that is just wrong.
嘿，伙计，可别小看他
I got two guys free in about 20 minutes!
我20分钟就找到两个人
Got it! Need them!
正好用得上
You're not in Kansas anymore.
这儿可不是堪萨斯
You are on Pandora, ladies and gentlemen.
这儿是潘多拉星球，女士们先生们
Respect that fact every second of every day.
请每时每刻记着这事实
If there is a hell,
如果世界上有地狱
you might want to go there for some R&R after a tour on Pandora.
那么和潘多拉星球比起来 那儿简直就是天堂了
Out there, beyond that fence,
在围栏的外面
every living thing that crawls, flies or squats in the mud
泥沼内所有肘、飞、游的生物
wants to kill you and eat your eyes for Jujubes.
都渴望把你生知活剥
We have an indigenous population of humanoids called the Na'vi.
那儿有一种土著居民名叫纳威人
They're fond of arrows dipped in a neurotoxin
他们喜欢使用一种浸有毒液的弓箭
that'll stop your heart in one minute.
能让你需刻间上每命
And they have bones reinforced with naturally occurring carbon fiber.
还长着贮纤维强化的骨头
They are very hard to kill.
很难杀死他们
As head of security, it is my job to keep you alive.
我身为保安队长 有责任让你们活着
I will not succeed.
可是我也许做不到
Not with all of you.
我只能尽力而为
If you wish to survive,
如果你们想活下去
you need to cultivate a strong mental attitude.
那就必须具有钢铁般的意志
You've got to obey the rules.
你们必须遵守规则
Pandora rules.
潘多拉的规则
Rule number one...
第一条规则是
There's nothing like an old-school safety brief
不会引用老套纪律
to put your mind at ease.
来令你们安心
Excuse me. Excuse me. Jake! You're Jake, right? Tom's brother.
对不起，杰克，你是杰克，汤米的兄弟
Wow! You look just like him.
你们长得可真像
Sorry, I'm Norm. Spellman. I went through avatar training with him.
对不起，我是诺曼斯候尔曼 我和汤米一起接受阿凡达培训
..into the bio-lab.
生物实验室
We're gonna spend a lot of time up here. Hey! How you doing? Norm, avatar driver.
我们要长期在这里工作 你好，诺曼，阿凡达控制员
-Hi. -Hey.
-嘿 - 隆
Link... Here's the link room right here.
链接室，这里就是链接室
This is where we're connecting to the avatar.
我们在这里遥距操控阿凡达
Me and Norm are here te drive
我和诺曼
these remotely controlled bodies called avatars.
将要在这里打控那些名为阿凡达的替身
And they're grown from human DNA mixed with the DNA of the natives.
他们是利用人类和当地土著人培育出来的
-Hey. Welcome. -Hey.
-阵，欢迎你们 - 隆
-Welcome to Pandora. Good to have you. -Thanks.
- 欢迎来到潘多拉，很高兴认识你们 - 谢谢
Damn! They got big.
见鬼，他们长大了
Yeah, they fully mature on the flight out.
是的，他们已经完全成熟
So the proprioceptive sims seem to work really well.
本体感知模拟器发育良好
Yeah, they've got great muscle tone.
是的，而且肌肉强健有力
It'll take us a few hours to get them decanted,
再有几个小时就可以出箱
but you guys can take them out tomorrow.
不过明天便可出去
There's yours.
那个是你的
Hey. Dr. Norm Spellman.
降，诺曼斯假尔曼博士
-Dr. Max Patel. Great to meet you. -Good to meet you, yeah.
- 事克斯假特尔博士，很高兴认识你 - 我也很高兴认识你
Looks like him.
长得很像他
No, it looks like you.
不，长得像你
This is your avatar now, Jake.
他现在是你的阿凡达，杰克
And the concept is that every driver fis matched to his own avatar,
他们的想法是让每个控制员 都和自己的阿凡达相匹配
so that their nervous systems are in tune,
使两者的神经系统协调
or something.
大概是这样
Which is why they offered me the gig, because I can link with Tommy's avatar,
这就是他们让我来这儿的原因 我可以和汤米的阿凡达匹配
which is insanely expensive.
阿凡达的造价高得惊人
Is this right? I just say whatever to the video log?
这样可以吗? 我的视频日记说什么都行吗?
Yeah, we gotta get in the habit of documenting everything.
是的，我们必须养成认真记录的习惯
You know, what we see, what we feel.
包括看到的和感觉到的
-It's all part of the science. -And good science is good observation.
- 这是科研的一部分 - 科学来自严谨的观察
Plus it'll help to keep you sane for the next six years.
这也有助于你在今后6年中保持清醒
All right. Whatever.
好吧，那好吧
So...
于是
Well, here lam,
我就这样
doing science.
搞起了科研
They're coming out!
他们要出来了
Attention. Drivers coming out of link.
注意，请控制员断开链接
Oh, God.
噢，上帝
Where's the lab coat?
工作服在哪儿?工作服在哪儿?
Who's got my goddamn cigarette? Guys! What's wrong with this picture?
你们谁拿着我的香烟呢? 伙计们，我手里怎么没有香烟?
-Thank you! -Grace Augustine is a legend.
- 谢谢 - 格划丝奥古斯丁是个传奇人物
She's the head of the Avatar Program. She wrote the book,
她是阿凡达计划的负责人 也是那本书的作者
I mean, literally wrote the book on Pandoran botany.
就是那本有关潘多拉植物学的著作
Well, that's ‘cause she likes plants better than people.
她喜欢植物远胜过喜欢人类
Here she is, Cinderella back from the ball.
舞会上回来的灰姑娘，格划丝
Grace, I'd like you to meet Norm Spellman and Jake Sully.
请允许我介绍诺曼斯修尔曼 和杰克萨利
Norm. I hear good things about you. How's your Na'‘vi?
诺曼，很多人都夸你，你的纳威语如何?
May the All Mother...
愿万能之母
smile upon our first meeting,
祝福我们的初次见面
Not bad. You sound a little formal.
还不错，只是稍感生硬
studied for five years...
我已经学了5年
...but there is much to learn.
不过还是差得很远
-Grace? This is Jake Sully. -Ma'am.
-格老丝，这位是杰克萨利 -夫人
Yeah, yeah. I know who you are, and I don't need you. I need your brother.
知道，我知道你是谁，可我不需要你 我需要你兄弟
You know, the PhD who trained for three years for this mission?
懂吗? 那位受过整整3年培训的博士
He's dead.
他死了
I know it's a big inconvenience for everyone.
我知道这是所有人的损失
-How much lab training have you had? -I dissected a frog once.
- 你参加过多少培训 - 我解剖过一只青蛙
You see? You see? I mean, they're just pissing on us
听听，了听见吗? 他们就是这样糊弄我们
without even the courtesy of calling it rain.
而且丝毫不加掩饰
-I'm going to Selfridge. -No, Grace,
- 我要去找塞弗里奇 -不，格荔丝
-I don't think that's a good idea. -No, man, this is such bullshit!
- 你最好别去 - 伙计，这简直是胡闹!
I'm gonna kick his corporate butt.
我要给他点颜色看看
He has no business sticking his nose in my department.
他根本不应该插手我的部门
Here tomorrow, 0800. Try and use big words.
了明天上午8点来这儿，以后说话注意点
Scorpion Two-Hotel, Hell's Gate tower. You are cleared for south departure.
天蝎2H，我是塔台，南面起飞
Hover taxi, Delta runway. Squawk ident.
滑行，D跑道，身份确认
-You see that? -Yes, sir.
- 看到没有? -是的，长官
No, you didn't. You were looking at the monitor.
你没看到，你在看监视器
I love this putter, Ronnie! I love this putter.
我喜欢这种推杆，罗尼 我喜欢这种推杆
Parker, you know, l used to think it was benign neglect,
帕克，我一直以为你只是漠视而已
but now I see that you're intentionally screwing me.
今天我才知道你是在成心跟我作对
Grace, you know, I enjoy our little talks.
格老丝，我就喜欢听你讲话
I need a researcher. Not some jarhead dropout.
我需研究员，不是退役海军
Well, actually, I thought we got lucky with him.
我认为找到他很幸运
-Lucky? -Yeah.
- 幸运? - 是的
How is this in any way lucky?
找到他有什么可幸运的?
Lucky your guy had a twin brother,
因为他是汤米的挛生兄弟
and lucky that brother wasn't some oral hygienist or something.
因为他恰好不是牙医什么的
A Marine we can use.
海军队员大有用处
I'm assigning him to your team as security escort.
我让他去你的部门担任保安
The last thing I need is another trigger-happy moron out there!
我最不需要的就是战争狂人
Look, look, you're supposed to be winning the hearts
听着，你要赢得当地土著人的喜爱
and the minds of the natives.
和他们的信任
Isn't that the whole point of your little puppet show?
这也是你研发阿凡达的目的
If you look like them and you talk like them,
只要他们长相一样，语言相通
then they'll start trusting us.
就可能赢得土著人的信任
We build them a school, we teach them English,
我们为他们建学校，教他们英语
but after, what, how many years?
可是这么多年过去了
Relations with the indigenous are only getting worse.
我们之间的关系日瘟恶化
Yeah, that tends to happen when you use machine guns on them.
这是因为你对他们使用武器的结果
Right. Come here.
没错，你过来
I can't... ] can't...
我不能…
This is why we're here. Unobtanium.
我们为它来到这里，超导和矿石
Because this little gray rock sells for 20 million a kilo.
只因为这块灰石卖二千万一公斤
That's the only reason. It's what pays for the whole party.
这就是原因所在 足以支付整个计划
It's what pays for your science.
支付你的科研
Now, those savages are threatening our whole operation,
那些野蛮人威胁到了我们事业的发展
we're on the brink of war,
战争一触即发
and you're supposed to be finding a diplomatic solution.
你应该寻找一种外交解决方案
So use what you've got, and get me some results.
利用你所有的，做出点成绩来
So, how much link time have you logged?
你完成了多少链接?
-About 520 hours. -That's good.
- 大约520小时左右 -很好
You're in there. You're here. How much have you logged?
你去那边 你在这，你的链接时间呢?
Zip. But l read a manual.
零，但我看过说明书
Tell me you're joking.
你简直开玩笑
This is cool.
真酷
Let's go.
来吧
Don't. I got this.
不用，我自己来
So you just figured you'd come out here,
你打算来这儿
to the most hostile environment known to man,
这个最恶人劣苛刻的环境
with no training of any kind, and see how it went?
全无准备地体验一下?
What was going through your head?
你到底在想什么?
Maybe I was sick of doctors telling me what I couldn't do.
可能我厌倦了医生的戒条
-Biometrics are good. -Link three is ready.
- 生理检查正常 - 3号仓准备
Keep your arms in, hands in, head down.
用膊放进去，还有手，躺下
Down. Just relax and let your mind go blank.
躺下，精神放松什么也不要去想
That shouldn't be hard for you.
这对你应该不困难
Kiss the darkest part of my lily white...
让你的偏见见鬼去
Initiate link.
局动链接
Run sequence unit three. Go.
运行3号仓程序，开始
Launching.
开始了
l have the first congruency.
首次合并
-That's a gorgeous brain. Nice activity. -Go figure.
- 真不是一般的大脑，异常活跃 - 真没想到
Phase-lock 40%.
合并率到达40%
All right. Going in.
好的，该我了
I'm going in in four.
我用4号仓
Phase-lock 99%. Link is stable.
合并率达到99%，链接稳定
He's in. Jake, can you hear me? Can you hear me, Jake?
合并完成，杰克，能听到我声音吗? 能听到吗，杰克?
Pupillary reflex is good.
瞳孔反射正常
Pinna response normal. How you feeling, Jake?
耳廓反应正常，感觉怎样? 杰克
Hey, guys.
阵，伙计们
Welcome to your new body, Jake.
欢迎你进入新躯壳，杰克
Good!
很好!
Yeah, we're gonna take this nice and easy, Jake.
我们需要慢慢适应，杰克
-And touch your thumb to your fingers. -Yeah.
- 用拇指触摸其它手指 - 好的
-Thumb to your fingers. -No problem.
- 用拇指触摸 - 没问题
That's good. I can see you can remember that one.
很好，看得出你还没有忘记
-Got it. -Well, if you want to sit up,
-完成了 - 如果你想坐起来
-that's fine. -Okay, good. Just take it
-可以的 - 动作要慢一些
nice and slow, Jake. Good. Okay, well, no truncal ataxia, that's good.
杰克，很好，躯干协调性很好，好极了
Are you feeling lightheaded or dizzy at all? You're wiggling your toes!
感到头重脚轻或者晕眩? 活动一下脚趾
-Good. Good, Jake. -That's great.
- 很好，杰克 - 好极了
Distal motor control is good. Good, Jake.
神经末端运动肌控制良好，很好，杰克
Are you feeling any numbness or pain?
是否有麻疗或疼痛的感觉
That's great, Jake. Hold on, now.
太好了了，杰克
Take it easy. Don't get ahead of yourself, okay?
不，动作慢点，不要操之过急，好吗?
There's a few more sensory motor reflex tests we need to run,
还要做感官反射测试
-so take it easy. -Wait.
- 不要急 - 等等
-Jake. -Sit down, Jake.
- 杰克 -坐下，杰克
Jake! Listen to me. Jake!
听我说，杰克
-l need you to sit down. Jake! -It's okay.
-我们要求你坐下，杰克 - 没事
-Buddy, listen to me. -It's all good. I got this.
- 伙计，听我说 - 感觉真好，我能走了
-Jake, you need to sit down right now. -Guys, get him back on the gurney now.
- 杰克，你马上给我坐下 - 伙计们，马上把他弄回床上
Listen to me. For your own safety, you need to sit down.
听我说，为了安全起见，你需要坐下
You need time to adjust to the avatar... Whoa! Jake!
适应阿凡达你得需要时间，杰克
-God, Jake, watch your tail. -Yeah!
- 杰克，当心尾巴 -好!
Sedate! Sedate him! A thousand milligrams of Supitocam! Stat!
镇静剂 ! 给他注射一千毫克苏比特康!
Guys! Guys! Whoa! Whoa!
伙计们，伙计们
By the numbers.
从数据上看
-Jake. Come on. -Jake! Listen to me.
- 杰克 - 昕我说
You're not used to your avatar body.
你还不适应你的阿凡达
-This is dangerous. -This is great.
- 这样做很危险 - 感觉真好
-Jake? Jake, listen to me. -Come on. They're gonna put you out.
- 杰克，上听我说 -别这样，他们要用镇静剂了
-Norm, sit down. -No, no. I gotta get out of these leads.
-诺曼，坐下 -不，不，我得弄掉这些电线
God damn it! Bring them home!
该死! 把他弄回来
-Norm! Do not leave control! -You're not ready for it!
-诺曼，不要急 - 你还没习惯
-Oh, come on, you ain't got no skills. -So close!
- 你根本不会打篮球 - 差一点!
I don't even have to play defense on it.
我根本不用防守
Hey, guys. Hey.
阵，伙计们
-It's okay, I'll get him. -Jake, you have to come back!
- 没关系，我去找他 - 杰克，你给我回来!
Jake! Jake! Excuse me.
杰克! 杰克! 对不起
-Watch it! -Sorry!
-小心! - 对不起!
Come on!
来!
Jake! We're not supposed to be running!
杰克，我们可不是来跑步的
-Jeez! Sorry. -Watch it!
-嗅，见鬼，对不起 -小心!
Hey, Marine!
降，海军!
Damn.
该死
-Grace? -Well, who'd you expect, numbnuts?
- 格需丝? -还能是谁? 笨蛋
Think fast.
思考敏捷
Motor control's looking good.
动力控制不错
Come on, everybody, quiet down! All right, gang, lights out.
好了，大家请安静 ! 好了，伙计们，熄灯了
Come on, Louise, chop-chop.
快点，露易丝，快点
Hey, hey, hey!
曙，嘿，嘿!
Don't play with that, you'll go blind.
别玩那个，小心型贞眼睛
That's kind of freaky.
好奇怪啊
Come on. Scat.
快点，请吧
Good night.
晚安
Lights out! See you at dinner, kiddies.
关灯了，晚饭见，孩子们
Welcome back.
欢迎回来
-You okay? You all right? -Yeah, I'm okay.
-怎么样，你还好吗? - 我很好
I'm Trudy. I fly all the science sorties. And this here is my baby.
我叫朱迪，负责所有科研飞行 这是我的坐骑
Hold on a second.
请稍等
Hey, Wainfleet! Get it done!
温弗利，修好它
-We bounce at zero-nine. -Yeah, I'm on it, capitaine!
-我们9点整起飞 - 好的，我明白，上尉
Vine strike's still loose.
防护醒还是有点松
You guys are packing some heavy gear.
你们在安装重型武器
Watch it!
当心!
Yeah, that's ‘cause we're not the only thing flying around out there.
是的，因为不是只有我们在那里能飞的
Or the biggest.
也不是最大的
I'm gonna need you on a door gun. I'm a man short.
我需要你担任机枪射手，我们差一个人
I thought you'd never ask.
还以为你不会问呢
There's your man. See you on the flight line.
你找的人在那儿，一会儿见
You wanted to see me, Colonel?
你找我，上校?
This low gravity'll make you soft.
地心引力低会使你变得虚弱
You get soft,
虚弱的人
Pandora will shit you out dead with zero warning.
在潘多拉星球将无法生存
I pulled your record, Corporal.
我看了你的档案，下士
Venezuela, that was some mean bush.
委内瑞拉是个蛮荒地带
Nothing like this here, though.
但远远比不上这儿
You got some heart, kid, showing up in this neighborhood.
你是个好样的，小伙子，敢到这里来
I figured it's just another hellhole.
大不了是另外一个地狱
I was First Recon myself.
我也曾是海军情报员
A few years ahead of you. Well, maybe more than a few.
早你几年，也许不止几年
Three tours Nigeria, not a scratch.
我去过三次尼日利亚，毫发无损
I come out here?
来这儿
Day one. Think I felt like a shavetail louie?
第一天，我就像个新陆军少尉
Yeah. They could fix me up, if l rotated back.
如果我回到地球，他们会给我整容
Yeah, and make me pretty again. But you know what? I kind of like it.
让我恢复英俊 但你知道吗? 我喜欢这样
It reminds me every day what's waiting out there.
它每天提醒我时刻警惕
The Avatar Program is a bad joke. Bunch of limp-dick science majors.
阿凡达计划是个可怕的玩笑 是那群科学家的无聊把戏
However, it does present an opportunity both timely and unique.
不过，计划带来了个独特及时的机会
-Clear!
-走开!
A recon gyrene in an avatar body. That's a potent mix.
海军情报员操控阿凡达，无敌组合
Give me the goose bumps.
让人异常兴奋
Such a Marine could provide the intel I need,
为我提供所需要的情报
right on the ground.
战场上的情报
Right in the hostiles’ camp.
和歼营内的情报
Look, Sully. I want you to learn these savages from the inside.
听着，杰克，我需要你 混入野变人里学习
I want you to gain their trust.
取得他们的信任
I need to know how to force their cooperation
我要知道如何才能迫使他们合作
or hammer them hard if they won't.
否则是将他们打垮
-Am I still with Augustine? -On paper.
- 我还受格世丝领导吗 - 理论上是
Yeah, you walk like one of her science pukes, you quack like one,
你还要跟那些科学怪物一样的 行动和说话
but you report to me.
但向我报告
Can you do that for me, son?
能做到蚂，小伙子?
Hell, yeah, sir.
是的，长官
Well, all right, then.
那就好
Son, I take care of my own.
小伙子，我很关照自己人
You get me what I need,
给到我所要的
I'll see to it you get your legs back when you rotate home.
回到地球后，我会让你有自己的腿
Your real legs.
你自己的双腿
That sounds real good, sir.
这话很诱人，长官
-Link's ready! -Phase-lock 40%.
- 准备链接 - 合并率40%
Just keep your mouth shut and let Norm do the talking.
你不要说话，有话让诺曼讲
Il have five congruencies. Phase-lock 90%.
合并正常，合并率90%
Link three ready.
3号仓准备好
All right, I'm going in.
好的，我进去了
Shut it down. We're gonna stay a while.
关掉发动机，我们会停留一会儿
-Norm! Your pack. -Pack.
-诺曼，你的氧气罩 - 你留下
Stay with the ship. One idiot with a gun is enough.
拿枪的笨蛋，一个就够了
You the man, Doc.
遭命，博士
Prolemuris. They're not aggressive.
狐猴，它们没有攻击性
Relax, Marine. You're making me nervous.
放松，海军，你令人紧张
So, how will they know we're here?
他们怎么知道我们来这儿
I'm sure they're watching us right now.
他们一定正在监视我们
-Keep moving, Norm. -Keep up, guys!
-快点，诺最 -跟上，伙计们
-And here I go. -Scanning.
-我们到了 - 开始扫描
-Amazing, isn't it? -Yeah.
- 想不到吧? - 真的
So, that is signal transduction from this root
这些信号从一棵树的根部
to the root of the tree next to it. So, we should take a sample.
传到与它相邻的另外一棵 我们开始取样本
Okay. Sample.
好的，样本
You know, it's probably electrical, based on the speed of the reaction.
依反应速度来看，应该是电子信号
Norm, you've contaminated the sample with your saliva.
诺曼，你的口水污染了样本
Right.
是的，对不起
So, here I go.
再来
Don't shoot. Don't shoot, you'll piss him off.
别开枪，那会激怒他
It's already pissed off.
他已经被激经了
Jake, that armor's too thick. Trust me.
杰克，他的甲壳坚不可摧，相信我
It's a territorial threat display. Do not run, or he'll charge.
它在展示领土防御威力，别跑，它会攻击
So, what do I do, dance with it?
我该怎么办?与他跳舞?
Just hold your ground.
你站好别动
Yeah? Come on! What you got?
来吧，有什么本领?
Oh, yeah. Who's bad? That's right.
谁伯谁呀? 对了
Yeah, that's what I'm talking about, bitch.
我可不是好营的
That's right, get your punk ass back to mommy.
这就对了，回去找你妈妈吧
Yeah? Yeah, you got nothing. You keep running.
对了，你胆子小，就会跑
Yeah, and why don't you bring back some of your friends, huh?
去把你的同伙叫来吧
Oh, shit.
哦，糟了
So what about this one? Run? Don't run? What?
这是什么东西? 跑还是不跑?
I'm gonna have te call it, guys.
我必须停止搜索，伙计们
We're not allowed to run night ops. Colonel's orders.
未经允许不得夜间飞行，上校的命令
I'm sorry, Doc, he's just gonna have to hang on till morning.
对不起，博士 他要撑到明早
He won't make it till morning.
他不可能撑到明天早晨
I don't have all goddamn night.
我没时间跟你玩
Come on! Come on!
来吧! 来吧!
Hey, wait. Don't!
等等不要!
Great.
好
Look, I know you probably don't understand this,
好吧，我知道你可能听不懂
but thank you.
但是谢谢你
Thank you.
谢谢你
That was pretty impressive.
身手不凡
I would have been screwed if you hadn't come along. It was...
如果没有你我可能就没命了
Hey, wait a second. Hey, where you going?
等一下，你去哪儿?
Wait up!
等等我!
Just... Hey, slow down.
慢点
Look, wait up, I just wanted to say thanks for killing those things.
我只想谢谢你帮有我杀死了那些怪兽
-Damn! -Don't thank.
- 见鬼 - 不用谢
You don't thank for this.
不应该说谢谢
This is sad. Very sad only.
这太可悲了，非常可翡
Okay. Okay. I'm sorry.
好吧，好吧，对不起
Whatever I did, l am sorry.
我为所做的道歉
All this is your fault. They did not need to die.
这都怪你，他们本来不应该死去
My fault? They attacked me. How am I the bad guy?
怪我，是他们攻击我，怎么能怪我?
Your fault!
就怪你
-Your fault! -Easy. Easy.
- 就怪你 - 别激动，别激动
You're like a baby. Making noise, don't know what to do.
你像婴儿般啤吸叫，不知所措
Easy.
别激动
Fine. Fine.
好吧，好吧
If you love your little forest friends,
如果你爱这些森林伙伴
why not let them just kill my ass?
那干嘛不让他们杀死我?
What's the thinking?
为什么救我?
-Why save you? -Yeah. Yeah, why save me?
- 为什么救你? - 对了呀，为什么救我?
You have a strong heart.
因为你很勇敢
No fear.
无畏惧
But stupid! Ignorant like a child.
可是你很春，无知得像个孩子
Well, if I'm like a child, then...
如果我像个孩子，你就
Look, maybe you should teach me.
那你该教导我
Sky People cannot learn. You do not See.
天空人学不会，你们看不见
Well, then teach me how to See.
那就告诉我怎么才能看见
-No one can teach you to See. -Whoa.
- 没人能够让你们看见 -了哦
Look, come on, can't we talk?
别这样，我们谈谈吗?
Say, where'd you learn to speak English? Dr. Augustine's school?
你在哪儿学的英语，在格划丝办的学校?
You're like a baby.
你真是个孩子
I need your help.
我需要你帮助
You should not be here.
你不该来这儿
-Okay, take me with you. -No! Go back.
- 带我走吧 -不! 你回去
No.
不
Go back.
回去
No!
不!
What...
什么
What are they?
它们是什么?
Seeds of the Sacred Tree.
他们是圣树的种子
Very pure spirits.
纯洁的精灵
What was that all about?
这是怎么回事?
Come.
来吧
Come!
来呀!
Where are we going?
我们去哪儿?
Come.
快点
What's your name?
你叫什么名字?
Okay.
好吧
Calrn people, calm.
大家别紧张，别紧张
What are you doing, Tsu'tey?
你做什么，苏泰
These demons are forbidden here.
这些魔鬼禁止来这里
There has been a sign.
刚才有启示了
This is a matter for the Tsahik.
关系到纳威人的精神领袖
Bring, him.
把他带走
What's going on?
怎么回事?
Wait.
等等
Hey!
嘿!
Father...
父亲
...1 see you.
我看到你
This creature...
这个家伙
why do you bring, him here?
你为何带他来这儿
l was going to kill him...
我本来想杀死他
..but there was a sign from Eywa.
可是艾华女神有启示了
have said...
我说过
+N dreamwalker will come here.
禁止阿凡达到这里来
What's he saying?
他在说什么?
His alien smell fills my nose.
外星人的气味太刺鼻了
Hey, what's he saying?
他说什么?
My father is deciding whether to kill you.
我父亲在考虑杀不杀你
Your father. It's nice to meet you, sir.
你父亲，很高兴认识你，先生
Step back!
退后!
I will look at this alien.
让我看看这个异类
That is Mother.
她是我母亲
She is 7sahik. The one who interprets the will of Eywa.
她是精神领袖，艾华女神意旨的传递者
Who's Eywa?
艾华女神是谁?
What are you called?
你叫什么名字?
Jake Sully.
杰克萨利
-Why did you come to us? -I came to learn.
- 你为什么来我们这里? - 我是来学习的
We have tried to teach other Sky People.
我们教过别的天空人
It is hard to fill a cup which is already full.
可是装满的杯子无法再加水
Well, my cup is empty, trust me.
我是空杯，相信我
Just ask Dr. Augustine. I'm no scientist.
你可以去问奥古斯丁博士 我不是科学家
What are you?
那你是什么?
I was a Marine. A...
前海军队员
A warrior of the Jarhead clan.
就是海陆部落战士
Awarrior!
一个战士!
t could kill him easily!
我能轻易杀死他 !
I could kl im easily!
不!
This is the first warrior dreamwalker...
他是第一个阿凡达战士
1 WE have seen.
迄今为目
We need to learn more about him.
我们需要认真研究他
My Daughter. .
我的女儿
+-YOu will teach him our way...
你负责教导他
«to speak and walk as We do.
让他像我们一样说话行走
Why me? That’s not fair...
为什么是我? 这不公平
It is decided. My daughter will teach you our ways.
决定了，今后由我女儿负责教导你
Learn well, Jakesully.
要好好学习，杰克萨利
Then we will see if your insanity can be cured.
看看能否治愈你的失常
Good evening.
晚上好
Please don't get up.
大家不用起来
Excuse me.
让一下
Sorry.
对不起
Hey, how you doing?
你好吗?
-Jake. Jake! -He's in alpha.
- 他要醒了
-He's coming out right now. -Jake. Jake!
-他正在醒来
Come on back, kid. Come on. That's it.
醒醒孩子，醒醒，好了
There you go. There you go, there you go.
好了，好了
You're okay. You're okay.
你没事，你很好
Damn! You were dug in like a tick.
该死，你投入得不想回来
-Is the avatar safe? -Yeah, Doc.
- 你的阿凡达还好吗? -是的，博士
And you are not gonna believe where I am.
你们想不到我去哪儿了
The last thing we see is this Marine's ass
我们只看到这倒霉的
disappearing into the brush with this angry thanator coming after him.
前海军队员逃进了丛林 身后那黑甲巨豹紧追不含
-Hey, it's not something you can teach. -That is awesome.
- 这本领你们教不来 - 太棒了
You know, for reasons I cannot fathom,
不知道因为什么
the Omaticaya have chosen you. God help us all.
那些野变人选了你，愿上帝保佑我们
“Jarhead clan"?
海军族?
-And it worked? -Hey, I'm practically family.
-他们相信? - 对，我是一家人了
They're gonna study me. I have to learn to be one of them.
他们准备研究我 我得学会像他们一样
That's called taking the initiative, son.
看来你掌握了主动权
-l wish I had 10 more like you. -Look, Sully. Sully.
-但愿多些像你这样的人 - 萨利
Just find out what the blue monkeys want.
你要了解那些野蛮人想要什么
You know, I mean, we try to give them medicine, education, roads.
我们试图为他们修建医院，学校和公路
But no, no, no, they like mud.
可是不灵，他们只喜欢土地
And that wouldn't bother me, it's just that they're...
不过那也没什么关系，只要他们…
Hey, can you... Can somebody just... Sector 12.
谁来帮有帮忙，12区
Okay, go, go, go, stop. Stop...
好，去，去，停
Rich, stop! That's... Jesus!
停下! 那是…天哪!
Their damn village happens to be resting on the richest unobtanium deposit
他们该死的村子，正好位于超导矿石 蕴藏最丰富的地区
within 200 klicks in any direction. I mean, look at all that cheddar!
四周方圆200公里，看吧 一个巨大的宝藏 !
-Well, who gets them to move? -Guess.
- 谁能让他们搬走? - 猜猜看
-What if they won't go? -I'm betting that they will.
- 如果他们不搬呢? - 我相信他们会搬的
Okay, okay, okay, okay, hey. Look. Look.
好吧，上听我说
Killing the indigenous looks bad,
杀死士著并不光彩
but there's one thing that shareholders hate more than bad press,
但比起负面新闻，股东们
and that's a bad quarterly statement. I didn't make up the rules.
更讨厌看到糟糕的季度报告 规则不是我制订的
So just find me a carrot that'll get them to move,
好好想办法说服他们搬走
otherwise it's gonna have to be all stick. Okay?
否则就只能动用武力了，明自吗?
You got three months. That's when the 'dozers get there.
给你3个月时间，堆土机会到来
Well, we're wasting time.
我们在浪费时间
I like this guy.
我喜欢这家伙
-Guys, right now... -Okay, let's run through them again.
- 伙计们，现在 - 好吧，我们再复习一次
Mo'‘at. Dragon lady.
姆亚，女首领
-Eytucan. -Eytukan. He's the clan leader.
- 埃图卡 - 埃图康，他是部落领袖
But she's the spiritual leader. Like a shaman.
姆亚是精神领袖，祭师
Got it.
知道了
-T'su'tey. -Tsu'tey.
- 苏泰 - 苏台
-He'll be the next clan leader.
-他是下任族长
-Neytiri. -She'll be the next 7sahik.
- 奈蒂莉 -她是下任精神领袖
They become a mated pair.
他俩是一对
-So who's this Eywa? -Who's Eywa?
-那么爱华女神是谁? - 爱华女神是谁?
Only their deity. Their goddess, made up of all living things.
是他们的女神，他们的圣母 无处不在
Everything they know!
无所不知
You'd know this if you had any training whatsoever.
受过训的人都知道
Who's got a date with the chief's daughter?
跟首领女儿约会是什么人?
-Come on. That's... -All right, knock it off, you two.
-行了，那不是… -行了，你们俩别亲了
Let's go. Village life starts early.
开始吧，纳威人习惯早起
Don't do anything unusually stupid.
你可千万不要做什么奏事
Easy, boy.
别紧张，小伙子
Pale is female.
帕丽是姑女
Okay. Easy, girl.
别紧张，小姑娘
That is tsaheylu. The bond.
这叫心灵合一，合体
Feel her heartbeat. Her breath.
感觉她的心跳 她的呼吸
Feel her strong legs.
她强有力的四胶
You may tell her what to do.
你可以发号施令
Inside.
用意念
For now, say where to go.
说吧，你想去的方向
Forward!
向前!
-You should go away. -No, you'd miss me.
- 你应该滚开了 - 不，你会想我的
I knew you could speak English.
我知道你懂英语
This alien will learn nothing...
这个外星人什么也学不会
wed rock sees more...
还不如一块石头
.look at him.
瞧他那模样
Again.
再来
If you want to hit this thing, it's gonna be complicated.
想攻打这个，有点难度
Your scan doesn't show the internal structure.
你们无法扫描它的内部结构
There's an outer row of columns.
外围是一圈立柱
Real heavy duty. There's a secondary ring here,
异常坚固，还有第二环和内环
and an inner ring. There's a core structure like a spiral.
其核心结构呈螺旋状
That's how they move up and down.
构成上下通道
We're gonna need accurate scans on every column.
我们要精确扫描每一根立柱
Roger that.
知道
What else can you tell us about the structure?
关于它的结构还有什么补充吗?
I'm guessing this secondary ring, that's also load-bearing.
我认为第二环，属于承重结构
-So where are we going? -Getting out of Dodge.
- 我们去哪儿? - 去另外一个地方
I'm not about to let Selfridge and Quaritch micro-manage this thing.
我不希望塞弗里奇和库里奇染指这项计划
There's a mobile link up at Site 26 we can work out of,
26号站点有移动链接台可供我们使用
way up in the mountains.
就在山上
The Hallelujah Mountains?
你说哈利路亚山
-That's right. -Are you serious?
- 没错 - 没开玩笑吧?
-Yeah. -Yes!
- 是的 -太好了!
The legendary floating mountains of Pandora. Heard of them?
传说中的潘多拉悬浮山，听说过吗?
We're getting close.
已经不远了
Yeah, look at my instruments.
是的，瞧我的仪器
Yep. We're in the Flux Vortex.
对，那是磁旋涡
We're VFR from here on.
从现在起只能VFR了
What's VFR?
什么叫VFR?
Means you gotta see where you're going.
就是目视飞行的意思
-You can't see anything. -Exactly. Ain't that a bitch?
- 可什么也看不到 - 没错，是不是想骂人?
Oh, my God.
我的天
You should see your faces.
真该看看你们的表情
Thank you for flying Air Pandora.
谢谢搭乘潘多拉航空
Welcome to camp.
欢迎来到营地
-So, this is my bunk. -This stuff is nasty.
- 好吧，这是我的床 - 这里真够脏的
-Norm, go under. -All right.
-诺曼，你睡下铺 - 好吧
-Grace didn't miss a thing. -Trudy, you'll take the top one.
-格荐丝知道了 - 朱迪，你上面的
She knew I was talking to the Colonel.
她知道我和上校谈过话
But l had what she needed, a way back in with the clan,
但她需要我跟族人搞好关系
so she's playing nice.
所以她继续装好人
All right. Jake, hang a left. You'll be in the link at the end.
好吧，杰克，向左转 你使用最里面的链接仓
Unit one. Beulah. She's the least glitchy.
1号仓，最叫我放心了
Holy shit!
天哪!
Do not look in her eye.
不要看她的眼睛
Jkranis not horse.
伊卡兰不是马
Once tsaheylu is made,
一旦完成了心灵合一
Jkran will fly with only one hunter in the whole life.
伊卡兰一辈子只跟随一个狂人
To become ¢éaronyu, hunter,
为了成为塔龙纽，就是猎人
you must choose your own skran and he must choose you.
你必须选择自己的伊卡兰 她也必须选择你
-When? -When you are ready.
-何时? - 等你准备好
Okay. This is video log 12.
好吧，这是第十二篇视频日记
Time's 2132.
时间是21点32分
Do I have to do this now? l really need to get some rack.
我现在必须做吗? 但我真的很困
No, now. When it's fresh.
不行，马上做，趁热打铁
Okay, location, shack,
好吧，地点，营地
and the days are starting to blur together.
日子开始变得混淆
The language is a pain, but, you know,
这种语言非常难学，不过
I figure it's like field-stripping a weapon. Just repetition, repetition.
我觉得这就像拆解枪支，靠的是反复练习
-Navi. -"Mari."
- 眼睛 - 眼镜
-Nari. -"Narrri"!
- 眼镜!
Narrrif
- 眼睛
Txur ni'ul. Stronger.
用力呼吸
Neytiri calls me skxawng. {t means moron.
奈蒂莉管我叫斯康，意思是白阁
This is a very important part of it.
这个非常重要
-Norm's attitude has improved lately. -l see you. I see you.
-诺曼的态度最近有了改变 - 看到你，看到你
But it's not just, “I'm seeing you in front of me,”
但不是指一般的看到
it's "Il see into you. I See you.”
而是指看透，看懂你
It's good he's back on board, but he thinks I'm a skxawng, too.
有他在很好 不过他也认为我是个斯康
“I'm accepting you. I understand you." So you gotta get this, okay?
是指我接受你，我理解你 你必须学懂这个，行吗?
I gotta run! Okay? Let's go.
要走了，好了，走吧
My feet are getting tougher. f can run farther every day.
我的腿脚越发强壮，每天跑得更远
have to trust my body to know what te do.
我要相信我的身体知道该怎么做
Yeah! Check it out!
看我的
Oh, crap!
该死!
Every day it's reading the trails, the tracks at the waterhole,
每天都要辨认林中小径，野兽足迹
the tiniest scents and sounds.
最微细的气味声音
She's always going on about the flow of energy, the spirits of animals.
奈蒂莉经常跟我讲，能量的流动 动物灵性
l really hope this tree-hugger crap isn't on the final.
希望期末考不要考环保这科
This isn't just about eye-hand coordination out there, you know.
那种练习不仅仅关系到手眼配合
You need to listen to what she says.
你需要聆听她说的每句话
Try to see the forest through her eyes.
通过她的角度去观察森林
Excuse me. This is my video log here.
对不起，这是我的视频日记
With Neytiri, it's learn fast or die.
跟奈蒂莉学不学好便只有死
You gotta be kidding me.
你开玩笑吧
1 talked Maat into letting Grace into the village.
我说服姆亚允许格雷丝回到村子里
Look howbig you are.
瞧你们都长大了
It's the first time since her schoal was closed down.
这是从前的学校被关闭后她第一次回来
You are so pretty.
你可真漂亮
No, you don't. Come back here.
不行，你不能走，给我回来
Bon appétit.
好好享用吧
Come on, Marine.
去睡吧，海军
I'm trying to understand this deep connection
我竭力想弄明白
the people have to the forest.
人类与森林之间的那种深刻联系
She talks about a network of energy
奈蒂莉跟我讲了能量网络
that flows through all living things.
能量在生物之间流动
She says all energy is only borrowed,
她说，所有能量都是借来的
and one day you have to give it back.
早晚有一天要归还
I see you...
我看到你
...Brother
兄弟
..and thank you.
谢谢你
Your spirit goes with Eywa.
你的精神与艾华女神同在
Your body stays behind...
你的身体留下来
...to become part of The People.
化作纳威人的一部分
A clean kill.
干得漂亮
You are ready.
你已经准备好了
Learning to ride anikran, we call them banshees,
学习驾驭伊卡兰，也就是魔鬼乌
is the test every young hunter has to pass.
是每个猎人都必须通过的考验
But to do that, you gotta go where the banshees are.
你必须找到魔鬼鸟的栖息地
Oo-rah.
好了
Now what?
现在怎样?
Jakesully will go first.
杰克萨利你先来
Now you choose your fkran. This you must feel inside.
挑选你的伊卡兰吧，你要用心去选择
If he also chooses you, move quick like showed.
如果他也选择了你，就快速行动
You will have one chance, Jake.
你只有一次机会，杰克
How willl know if he chooses me?
我怎么知道他选择了我
He will try to kill you.
它会试图杀死你
Outstanding.
非常好
Let's dance.
来跳舞吧
That moron's going to die.
那白病死定了
Don't be afraid, warrior.
别害怕，战士
Make the bond!
合体!
No!
不!
Jake!
杰克 !
Tsaheylu, Jake.
心灵合一，杰克
Tsaheylu!
心灵合一
Stop!
停!
Yeah, that's right. You're mine. Huh?
这就对了，你是我的?
First flight seals the bond. You cannot wait.
首次飞行落实结合，机不可失
-Think, "Fly!" -Fly?
-用意念，“ 飞翔” - 飞翔?
God damn!
该死的!
Oh, shit!
见鬼!
Shut up and fly straight!
别南了，往前飞
That's it. Bank left!
对了，向左转
Level out! That's it.
回复平衡，干得好
Jakesully!
杰克萨利
Hey!
好啊!
Let's go!
来吧!
Yeah, baby, I got this!
宝贝儿，我成功了!
Oh, shit!
见鬼，不!
i may not be much of a horse guy, but l was bern to de this.
也许我天生骑不了马 但我骑这个却是天生的
Yeah!
是的!
-l came like this. This you. -Yeah, yeah.
-我像这样飞，你这样 -对，对
-I turn. I feel the wind. I turn very strong. -Look, yeah, see, I banked so hard...
- 我转弯时风阻很大，我非常用力 -我在斜飞时更加用力
The Tree of Souls.
灵魂树
It's their most sacred place.
他们最神圣的地方
See the Flux Vortex in these false color images?
看到这些假彩色显示的磁旋涡吗
Yeah, that's what messes up my instruments.
就是它们干扰了我的飞行仪表
There is something really interesting going on in there biologically.
从生物学角度讲 那里的确是个令人感兴趣的地方
I would die to get samples.
我非常想得到它的样本
Outsiders are strictly forbidden.
可是外人绝对不允许进入
You lucky swine.
你真幸运
! was a stone-cold aerial hunter. Death from above.
我曾经是一个空中冷血猎人 从天空猎杀
Only problem is, you're not the only one.
然而问题是，你不是唯一的杀手
Dive!
俯冲
Go, go!
快，快!
Follow me!
跟上!
Our guys call it a Great Leonopteryx.
我们的人管它叫做皇虹鸟
It is Toruk. Last Shadow.
它叫吐鲁克，意思是终影
Yeah, right. It's the last one you ever see.
没错，见到的最终影像
My grandfather's grandfather was Toruk Macto.
我曾曾祖父是个吐鲁克马克多
Rider of Last Shadow.
也就是终影骑士
He rode this?
他骑这个?
Toruk chose him.
是终影选择了他
It has only happened five times since the time of the First Songs.
有史以来那种事只发生过5次
-That's a long time. -Yes.
- 非常罕见 - 是的
Toruk Macto was mighty.
吐鲁克马克多无比强大
He brought the clans together in a time of great sorrow.
他在最危险的时刻把我们凝聚起来
All Na'vi people know the story.
纳威人都知道这个故事
Everything is backwards now. Like out there is the true world
一切都被颠倒了 好像那边才是真实的世界
and in here is the dream.
这儿只是梦境
It's hard to believe it's only been three months.
你很难相信时间只过了三个月
I can barely remember my old life.
已完全忘记以前的生活
I don't know who lam anymore.
我已忘了自己是谁
Haven't gotten lost in the woods, have you?
你是不是在森林里迷路了
Your last report was more than two weeks ago.
你上份报告是两星期前了
I'm starting to doubt your resolve!
我甚至开始怀疑你的斗志
The way I see it, it's time to terminate the mission.
看来，这项任务应该结束了
No, I can do this.
不，我可以完成
You already have.
你已经完成了
You give me good, usable intel.
你为我提供的情报至关重要
This Tree of Souls place.
掌握了灵树的位置
Yeah, I got them by the balls with that when this turns into a shit fight,
有这把柄在手，作战时逼他们就范
which it will. Yeah.
战争不可避免
Now it's time to come in.
现在你该回来了
By the way,
另外
you gonna get your legs back.
你可以有双新的腿
Yeah. I got your corporate approval. It's a done deal.
是的，已取得批准 达成了协议
Gonna have you ona shuttle tonight.
今晚派专机送你回地球
I'm a man of my word.
我是个守信的人
I gotta finish this.
我得完成这个
There's one more thing.
还有一件事
Ceremony. It's the final stage of becoming a man.
一个仪式，成为纳威族人的最后环节
If I do it, I'm one of them.
从此我就是他们一份子
And they'll trust me.
他们会信任我
And I can negotiate the terms of their relocation.
我可以劝他们选择新的居住地
Well, then, you'd better get it done, Corporal.
但愿能像你说的那样，下士
The Na'vi say that every person is born twice.
纳威人说每个人都会出生两次
The second time is when you earn your place among The People forever.
第二次出生就是当你赢取到族人 永恒的尊重
You are now ason of the Omaticaya.
你现在是奥马蒂卡亚部落之子
You are part of The People.
你成为了纳威人
Come. Come.
来吧，来呀
This is a place for prayers to be heard.
这是神灵接受祈祷的地方
And sometimes answered.
甚至可听到回应
We call these trees Utraya Mokri.
这些树名叫奥特拉亚莫克力
The Tree of Voices.
意思是声音之树
The voices of our ancestors.
是来自祖先的声音
I can hear them.
我听到了
They live, Jake,
他们还活着，杰克
within Eywa.
在艾华女神的怀里
You are Omaticaya now.
你已经属于奥马蒂卡亚了
You may make your bow from the wood of Hometree.
你要用家园树的枝干做一把弓剑
And you may choose a woman.
你还要选择一个女人
We have many fine women.
我们有很多漂亮姑娘
Ninat is the best singer.
妮纳特是最好的歌手
But I don't want Ninat.
我不要妮纳特
Peyral is a good hunter.
佩拉莉是个好狂人
Yeah, she is a good hunter.
是的，她的确是
I've already chosen.
可我已经选择了
But this woman must also choose me.
不过那姑娘也必须选择我
She already has.
她已经选择你了
lam with you now, Jake.
我是你的了，杰克
We are mated for life.
我们此生不渝
What the hell are you doing, Jake?
你干了什么，杰克?
Ma Jake!
杰克 !
Don't forget your phase integration.
别忘了你的链接进程
-Jake! -No, no, the middle button.
- 杰克! - 中间的按钮
-You gotta eat something. -Yeah, there you go.
- 杰克，你该吃点东西了 - 对，就是那个
Jake! Jake. Wake up! Jake, please!
杰克! 杰克，醒醒! 杰克，醒醒!
Don't make me force-feed a cripple.
别要我喂你这足子
Grace, I don't want... Hey!
格荔丝，我不想
Here. I'm done. Let's go.
吃好了，开始吧
And when was the last time you took a shower?
你有多长时间没洗澡了
- don't need a shower. -Jesus, Marine.
- 我不需要洗澡 -天哪，海军真离谱
Jake!
杰克 !
Jake! Wake up! Jake! Wake up!
杰克! 杰克，醒醒! 杰克，醒醒!
Hey!
嘿!
Stop! Stop!
停下! 停下!
-Jake! -Go back, stop!
- 杰克! -滚回去，停下!
Hey, boss.
老板
Hey!
站住
-What? -I got a native
-怎么了? - 有个张牙舞爪的土著人
doing the funky chicken here. He's blocking my blade.
挡住了我的去路
Well, keep going. He'll move.
虽，你走你的，他会躲开
These people have to learn that we don't stop. Come on, go, go, go.
让他们明和我们不会退缩 走吧，走
Stop! Hey!
停下!
Go! Go!
快! 快!
There, see? He moved.
看到没有，他躲开了
Dude, dude. Whoa, dude! Dude, no!
老兄，不，老兄，不!
I'm blind.
我看不见了
-Jake! -Neytiri!
- 杰克 - 奈蒂莉
Here, come on!
快点，快跑，来这边!
Freeze it right there.
停在那儿
Scale up. Enhance.
放大，调清楚点
Son of a bitch.
该死的东西
Unbelievable.
真不敢相信
-Get me a pilot. -Yes, sir.
- 叫飞行员来 -是，长官
Tsu'tey will lead the war party.
苏泰来指挥战队
Stop please
大家安静
This will only make it worse.
这样做只能使情况更精
You do not speak here!
你给我闭嘴
We will strike them in the heart.
我们要一举歼灭他们
Tsu'tey! Don't do this.
苏泰，不能这样做
-You! -Listen. Brother...
-你 一 兄弟…
-You mated with this woman? -Oh, shit.
- 你和这女子结合? -嗅，见鬼
Is this true?
这是真的吗?
We are mated before Eywa. It is done.
我们在艾华女神面前结合，是真的
Brother, please.
兄弟，求你了
Do not attack the Sky People. Many Omaticaya will die if you do.
不能别攻打天空人 奥马蒂卡亚将会血流成河
You are not my brother!
你不是我兄弟
And lam not your enemy!
我不是你的敌人
The enemy is out there, and they are very powerful!
敌人在那里，他们非常的强大
Go! Go! Go!
快! 快! 快!
-I can talk to them. -No more talk.
- 我可以去谈判 - 我不要谈判
Tsu'tey!
苏泰!
lam Omaticaya. I am one of you.
我属于奥马蒂卡亚，我们是一家人
And I have the right to speak.
我有说话的权力
have something to say...
我有话要说
...to all of you.
跟所有人
The words are like stones in my heart.
这些话就像石头讨在心底
Sir, I'm sorry. No, no, no! Hold on!
长官，对不起，不，不!
You can't interrupt a link in progress!
你不能在工作时断开链接
It's very dangerous!
那样做非常危险
Grace!
格荔丝
Oh, no.
噢，不
-Wait! -Stay down, sir.
- 等等! - 不许动，先生
Okay. Look...
好吧，了听着
I was sent here to...
我是被派来
You see?
看到吗?
It is a demon ina false body.
这被魔鬼依附的假身
-Are you out of your goddamn mind? -You crossed the line.
- 你疯了吗? - 你超越了底线
Wheel this meat out of here.
把这废物给我带走
Jake! What the hell is going on here?
杰克，出了什么事?
You let me down, son.
我对你很失望，孩子
So, what,
那又怎样
you find yourself some local tail
听着，你为自己找到了土著人的尾巴
and you just completely forget what team you're playing for?
可是却忘记了自己真正的使命
Parker, there is time to salvage the situation.
帕克，你现在还来得及扭转局面
-Parker... -Shut your pie hole!
- 帕克 -闭上你的臭嘴!
Or what, Ranger Rick? You gonna shoot me?
干什么，大队长? 开枪脆了我?
-I could do that. -You need to muzzle your dog.
- 别以为我不敢 - 你得管教管教你的部下
Yeah, can we just take this down a couple of notches, please?
好吧，我们大家都消消气好不好
You say you want to keep your people alive?
你想让你的人活下去吗?
You start by listening to her.
那就听听她怎么说
Those trees were sacred to the Omaticaya
那些树是奥马蒂卡亚的神灵
-in a way you can't imagine. -You know what?
- 你们无法想象 -嗅，知道吗?
You throw a stick in the air around here,
在这里只要随便扔一根树枝
it's gonna land on some sacred fern,
就能磺到他们的某个神灵
-for Christ's sake! -I'm not talking
- 天啊 -我指的不是平常所说的
about some kind of pagan voodoo here. I'm talking about something real,
巫术迷信，我说的是那种实实在在的
something measurable in the biology of the forest.
而是真实可度量的生物物质
Which is what, exactly?
你能具体些吗?
What we think we know
我们认为在树根与树根之间
is that there is some kind of electrochemical communication
有些电子化学联系
between the roots of the trees, like the synapses between neurons.
类似神经元之间的触突
And each tree has ten-to-the-fourth connections to the trees around it.
每棵树可联系周围一万棵树
And there are ten-to-the-twelfth trees on Pandora.
潘多拉星球有一万亿棵树
Which is a lot, I'm guessing.
那是很大一片
It's more connections than the human brain.
其复杂程度甚至超过了人类大脑
Get it? It's a network.
明自吗? 那是个网络
It's a global network, and the Na'vi can access it.
星球网络，一个纳威人能够进入的网络
They can upload and download data. Memories.
可以上传下载数据和记忆
At sites like the one you just destroyed.
你们刚才毁掉的就是它的网络站点
Yes!
明白吗!
What the hell have you people been smoking out there?
你们吸食了什么鬼东西
They're just goddamn trees!
那不过是该死的树而已!
-You need to wake up, Parker. -No. You need to wake up.
- 你该醒本了，帕克 - 不，该醒的人是你
The wealth of this world isn't in the ground. It's all around us.
这个星球上的财富并非只在地下 它无处不在
The Na'vi know that, and they are fighting to defend it.
纳威人知道，所以他们拆死保卫
If you want to share this world with them, you need to understand them.
如果你们想和他们共享财富 那就必须了解他们
I'd say we understand them just fine, thanks to Jake here.
应该说我才非常了解他们
Hey, Doc, come take a look.
噬，博士，你过来看
They're not gonna give up their home.
他们不会放弃家园
They're not gonna make a deal.
也不会跟我们做交易
For what? Lite beer?
交易什么? 啤酒?
And blue jeans?
牛仔裤?
There's nothing that we have that they want.
我们有的他们统统不要
Everything they sent me out here to do is a waste of time.
你们派我去那里去等于浪费时间
They're never gonna leave Hometree.
他们永远不会离开家园树
So, since a deal can't be made, I guess things get real simple.
好吧，既然不能达成交易 那事情就好办了
Jake, thanks. I'm getting all emotional.
杰克，谢谢你，我非常感动
I might just give you a big wet kiss.
我要给你一个大大的拥抱
I'll do it with minimal casualties to the indigenous.
我将以最小的代价赶走那些土著人
I'll drive them out with gas first.
首先我要动用催泪瓦斯
It'll be humane.
很人道的
More or less.
相对而言
All right, let's pull the trigger.
好吧，那就开始吧
-Come on, people. -Oh, man.
-来，快点 -嗅，天哪
Let's pack it up, let's go.
快点准备，走吧
This is how it's done.
原来如此
When people are sitting on shit that you want,
当别人拥有你想要的地方
you make them your enemy. Then you're justified in taking it.
就把他们变成敌人，然后理直气壮地摧毁
Quaritch is rolling the gunships. He's gonna hit Hometree.
库里奇正在调动飞机，他准备攻打家园树
My God.
天哪
-Dr. Augustine! You cannot be up here! -Back off!
- 奥古斯丁博士，你不可以来这里 - 走开
Parker. Wait. Stop. These are people you're about to...
帕克，等等，停下 你不能对那些苹良的人…
-No. No, no, no, no. -I said back off!
-不，不是 -我让你走开!
They're fly-bitten savages that live in a tree!
他们是无知的野变人，还住在树洞里!
All right? Look around!
看看周围吧 !
I don't know about you, but I see a lot of trees! They can move!
你看到什么，我看到无边的森林! 他们可以搬走
-Can you guys just please... -Yes, sir.
- 你们都走开 -是，先生
There are families in there. There are children. Babies.
那里有很多家庭，有孩子，婴儿
Are you gonna kill children?
你真的要杀他们
You don't want that kind of blood on your hands. Believe me.
你一定不希望双手沾满鲜血，我敢肯定
Just let me try to talk them out.
你就答应让我去谈判吧
They trust me.
他们信任我
Calibrate fast. We're going in, right now.
校准设备，准备链接，马上
Calibrating three and four.
3号和4号仓开始校准
-Run sequence. -Initiating. Thirty seconds.
- 运行程序 - 开始初始化30秒
Listen to me. You've got one hour.
你听好了，你们只有一小时
Unless you want your girlfriend in there when the ax comes down,
你想在屠刀落下前保住女友的性命
you get them to evacuate. One hour.
让他们赶快滚开，1小时
Father !
父亲
Mother !
母亲
Eytukan, t have something to say.
埃图康，我有话要说
Listen!
请听
Speak, Jakesully.
说吧，杰克萨利
A great evil is upon us...
灾难就要降临了
The Sky People are coming...
天空人要来
sto destroy Hometree.
拱毁我们的家园树
Look, tell them they're gonna be here soon.
告诉大家他们就要来了
You have to leave, or you're gonna die.
你们必须离开，不然会大祸临头
Are you certain of this?
真的会那样吗?
Look, they sent me here to learn your ways
他们派我来这儿，学习你们的生活
so one day I could bring this message and that you would believe it.
让我传递讯息，好让你们相信
What are you saying, Jake? You knew this would happen?
你说什么?杰克，这件事你早就知道?
Yes.
是的
Look, at first it was just orders,
最初，我只是服从命令
and then everything changed.
后来，一切都改变了
Okay? I fell in love.
我圣入了爱河
I fell in love with the forest and with the Omaticaya people.
我爱上了森林，爱上了奥马蒂卡亚人
And with you.
爱上了你
-I trusted you. -With you. With you.
- 我竟然会相信你 -我爱你
-I trusted you! -Trust me now, please.
-我这么信任你 - 请相信我
You will never be one of The People!
你永远不会成为我们的人!
-I shouldn't have... -We tried to stop them!
- 你永远不会成为我们的人 -我们试图阻止他们
Neytiri, please! Please.
奈蒂莉，求求你!
Bind them.
绑起他们
Leave now!
快离开!
You have to go. They're coming!
你们必须离开，他们要来了!
Time on target, one mike.
距离目标还有一分外
Copy. We have a visual.
了明白，我们已经看到目标
Roger that. Stay on heading 030.
收到，保持航向，方位0-3 -0
Roger, 030.
了明白，方位0-3 -0
-Run to the forest! -They're coming!
- 快到森林里去 ! -他们来了!
-They will destroy this place. -Neytiri, you must go now!
- 他们会把这里夷为平地 -奈蒂莉，你必须赶紧离开!
Run to the forest! Run!
快进森林，走!
Run! Run!
走! 走!
Have no fear.
不要害怕
No! God damn it, run!
不，该死，快跑!
Take the ikran...
带上伊卡兰
..attack from above.
从空中发动获击
That is one big damn tree.
好大的一棵树
Well, well, well. I'd say diplomacy has failed.
如此看来外交失败了
All right, people, let's get this done!
好了，伙计们，那就开始吧 !
I want every gas round you got right in the front door.
催泪瓦斯弹攻击正门
Roger. CS .40's going hot.
了明自，准备发射CS-40
-Fire. -Firing.
- 发射
Bingo. Mighty good shooting, ace.
正中，非常准
Sir, they've opened fire.
长官，他们还击了
You've got to be kidding me!
开什么玩笑!
These dumb bastards ain't getting the message.
那群笨蛋还搞不清楚
All right, let's turn up the heat.
给他们来点厉害的
-Switch incendiaries! -Switching incendiaries.
- 改用燃烧弹
Fire.
发射
No!
不!
Get everyone to the forest.
大家都到撤到森林里去
And that's how you scatter the roaches.
这跟消灭里螂没什么两样
Neytiri!
奈蒂莉!
We gotta move! He's gonna blow the columns!
我们必须离开，他们要炸毁立柱
My God!
天哪!
-Mo'at! No! -If you are one of us,
- 姆亚，不! - 如果你是我们的人
help us.
帮帮有我们
All call signs, switch missiles.
全体注意，改用导弹
Give me HE’'s at the base of the west columns.
向西边的支柱底部开火
This way!
这边!
Rider section, switch missiles.
R队准备换导弹
-One's goad. -Twa's rocks up.
-1号完毕 - 2号就位
-Three's up. -Yeah, baby, get some!
- 3号就位 - 好，给你点颜色 !
Charlie Oscar, Gunrunner standing by.
总司令，枪手待命
-Bring it down. -Cleared hat.
- 给我炸烂它 - 命令发射
Down! Head down!
中下!
Come on, come on! Down!
快，   快，   路下 !
-Solid hits. -Solid rocks on target.
-射中了 -正中目标
Screw this.
去死吧
Hey! What the hell are you doing?
降，你在干什么
I didn't sign up for this shit!
我来这不是为干这个
Repeat. Ripple fire.
重复，分散射击
Go! Go! Go!
走，走，快走!
No, no, get back! Back!
不，后退! 后退!
Come on! Come on, move! Move!
快点，快! 走!
That's good work, people. First round's on me tonight.
干得好，伙计们，今天晚上我请喝酒
Let's boogie.
走吧
Dragon coming left, heading home.
左转弯，返航
Gunrunner coming left.
枪手在左侧
-Thunder copies. -Rider section copies.
- 明白
Father !
父亲!
Daughte an
女儿
take...my...bow.
拿着我的弓
Protect The People.
保护好纳威人
Neytiri!
奈蒂莉!
-I'm sorry. I'm sorry. -Get away.
- 对不起，对不起 - 你走开
Get away!
走开!
Get away from here!
从这儿消失!
Never come back!
永远不要回来 !
Pull the plug.
断开链接
-No, you can't do that! -You can't do that!
-不，不行，你不可以! -不，不能这样做!
-Calm down! Calm down! -No! Please!
-冷静些! 冷静些! -不
l was a warrior whe dreamed he could bring peace.
我是个梦想和平的战士
Sooner or later, though, you always have to wake up.
早晚有一天，你们都会醒来
Let's go!
走吧!
Put him down!
放下他!
You murderer!
凶手!
What's going on, brother? Long time no see.
怎么样，伙计们，好久不见了
Hey.
嘿
Personally, I don't feel these tree-hugging traitors deserve steak.
这些叛变分子怎么可以吃牛排
They get steak? That's bullshit. Let me see that.
吃牛排? 胡说，看看
Yeah. You know what that is. Down.
你明白我意思，中下
-Trudy! -All the way down.
-朱迪! - 中到地上
Max!
麦克斯!
Trudy, fire up the ship! Go!
朱迪，发动战机! 快!
Here.
拿着
-Clear. Come on. -Here you go.
-安全，快点 - 拿着
Max, stay here. I need someone on the inside I can trust.
麦克斯，你留下 我们需要可信的人在这里
Okay. Go.
好吧，快走
Clear.
正常
Come on, baby.
快点，孩子
Colonel? Sir? I got a situation here.
上校，长官，这里有情况
It's Samson 1-6. Unauthorized engine start.
大力神16战机擅自启动
Three!
二 一
Come on!
快点!
Mask on!
戴氧气量!
Gas, gas, gas!
加油，加油!
I'm taking fire! Let's go!
我受到攻击! 快走!
Grab my hand! Come on, we're in. Let's go!
抓住我的手! 上来了，起飞!
Come on, let's go! Let's go, go!
快，快，快!
Colonel!
上校!
-Yeah! Yeah! -All right! Yes!
- 太棒了! -耶!
-Crap. -Everybody all right back there?
- 见鬼 - 后面的人没事吧?
Oh, yeah, baby!
是的，伙计!
-Norm, you good? -Yeah!
-诺曼，你还好吗? -很好!
This is gonna ruin my whole day.
看来我有点不太好
-Grace is hit! -What?
- 格绅丝中了枪 -什么?
-Get the trauma kit. -Trauma kit!
- 快拿急救包来 -急救包!
-Keep the pressure on, Grace. -Trauma kit's forward, on the bulkhead.
- 用力按着 -急救包在前面的舱壁内
-Hang on, Grace. -Doesn't matter. It's fine.
-坚持住，格攻丝 - 没关系，我没事儿
-You're goad to ga. -Take it up!
-可以走了 - 吊上来!
Hold on. I'm pulling pitch.
坐稳，我要起飞了
You're clear!
一切正常 !
Just keep going north. Get us deep in the mountains.
一直向北飞，深入山中
Copy that.
明白
-Norm, you all good up there? -Yep! Still here.
-诺曼，你没事吧? -是的，没事
Well, at least they can't track us up here. Not this far into the Vortex.
他们是不可能追到这里的 磁旋涡太强烈了
It's strongest at the Tree of Souls, right?
灵树一带最强烈，对吗?
Yeah.
是的
Good. 'Cause that's where we're going.
那好，我们就去那里
Ouch.
好疼
You big baby.
你这大孩子
We're moving.
我们在飞行
I'm gonna get you some help, Grace.
我们去找人救你，格划丝
I'm a scientist, remember?
我是科学家，别忘了
I don't believe in fairy tales.
我不相信童话
The People can help you.
纳威人会帮助你的
I know it.
我知道
Why would they help us?
他们和赁什么帮有我们?
The People say Eywa will provide.
纳威人说，艾华女神自有安排
With ne home, ne hope,
没有家，没有希望
there was only one place they could ga.
他们只有一个地方可去
Link's running.
正在链接
-What's the plan here, Jake? -There's no plan.
- 你打算怎么办，杰克? - 我还没想好
Tsu'tey is Olo'eyktan now. He's not gonna let you near that place.
苏泰现在是部落首领 他不会让你去那儿的
I gotta try.
我必须试试
Launching.
开始
Outcast.
放逐者
Betrayer.
叛徒
l was in the place the eye does not see.
我成了一个被遗弃的人
needed their help, and they needed mine.
我需要他们帮助 他们也需要我
But to ever face them again,
只要能够重新面对他们
i was gonna have to take it to a whole new level.
我必须设法更高层次地证明自己
Sometimes your whole life boils down to one insane move.
着那间的决定往往主宰人生
There's something we gotta do.
有些事我们不得不做
You're not gonna like it.
不管你想不想做
The way I had it figured, Toruk fs the baddest cat in the sky.
我认为吐鲁克是天上最可怕的飞兽
Nothing attacks him.
无人可以匹敌
Easy, boy.
小心，伙计
So why would he ever look up?
他为什么会现身呢?
But that was just a theory.
不过那只是我的想法
Toruk Macto?
终影骑士
I] See you.
我看到你
I was afraid, Jake.
我害怕，杰克
For my people.
为我的人民
I'm not anymore.
现在我放心了
Tsu'tey, son of Ateyo...
苏泰，阿蒂耶的儿子
...l stand before you...
我来到你面前
ready to serve the Omaticaya people.
准备为奥马蒂卡亚人效忠
You are Ofo'eyktan, and you are a great warrior.
你是部落首领和伟大的战士
I can't do this without you.
我需要你辅佐
Toruk Macteo,
终影骑士
I will fly with you.
我愿意追随你
My friend is dying.
我朋友快死了
Grace is dying.
格老丝要死了
I beg the help of Eywa.
我祈求艾华女神帮助
Look where we are, Grace.
看我们到哪儿了，格世丝
I need to take some samples.
我真想取些样本
The Great Mother may choose to save all that she is
全能之母将托救
in this body.
这躯体内
Is that possible?
有那种可能吗?
She must pass through the eye of Eywa and return.
她要通过艾华女神眼睛再回来
But, Jakesully,
可是杰克萨利
she is very weak.
她太虚弱了
Hang on, Grace. They're gonna fix you up.
坚持，格荔丝，他们会给你治好的
Hear us please, All Mother.
全能之母艾华请听
Eywa, help her.
救救她
Take this spirit into you...
请带走这个灵魂
..and breathe her back to us.
然后把她送还给我们
Let her walk among, us...
让她在我们中间行走
..as one of The People.
就像我们自己人一样
Grace.
格荔丝
I'm with her, Jake.
我和她在一起，杰克
She's real!
她真的存在
Grace? Grace, please. Grace!
格荔丝，格韦丝
What's happening?
怎么了?
Grace!
格老丝!
Did it work?
有效吗?
Her wounds were too great. It was not enough time.
她的伤势太重了，时间也太紧
She is with Eywa now.
她和艾华女神在一起了
With your permission, I will speak now.
请你允许，我有话要说
You would honor me by translating.
请屈苯为我翻译
The Sky People have sent us a message
天空人送来消息说
that they can take whatever they want
他们可以为所和欲为
and no one can stop them.
而且无人可政
Well, we will send them a message.
我们也有消息送给他们
You ride out as fast as the wind can carry you.
你们要像疾风一样出发
You tell the other clans to come.
号召其它所有的部落
You tell them 7oruk Macto calls to them.
就说终影骑士在召唤他们
And you fly now with me!
要马上行动，跟着我
My brothers! Sisters!
我的兄弟们，姐妹们
And we will show the Sky People
我们要告诉天空人
that they cannot take whatever they want,
他们不可以为所和欲为
and that this,
在这里
this is our land!
永远是我们的土地
Yah!
出发
We rede out to the four winds.
我们走遍四面八方
To the horse clans of the plain.
马族部落所在的平原
Back to the stars!
回去吧!
To the ikran people of the Eastern Sea.
伊卡兰人所在的东海
For our children's children!
为了我们的子孙
When Toruk Macto called them, they came.
听到终影骑士的召唤，他们都来了
Yah!
我们要战斗!
Everyone on this base, every one of you,
我们基地的成员，包括所有人
is fighting for survival.
都要为生存而战
There's an aboriginal horde out there massing for an attack.
土著部落正在招兵买马准备发动进攻
Now, these orbital images tell me
目前根据卫星图片显示
that the hostiles' numbers have gone from a few hundred
那些暴民已经在一天之内从数百人
to well over 2,000 in one day.
增加到了两千多人
And more are pouring in.
还有更多人正在汇集
In a week's time, there could be 20,000 of them.
一周之内人数可能会达到两万
At that point, they will overrun our perimeter.
到那时他们就会冲破我们的防线
Well, that's not gonna happen!
但我们绝不能等死
Our only security lies in pre-emptive attack.
我们要想战胜他们就必须先发制人
We will fight terror with terror.
我们要以暴制暴
Now, the hostiles believe that this mountain stronghold of theirs
他们相信山上的据点
is protected by their...
受到了神的保佑
Their deity.
他们的神灵
And when we destroy it,
一旦我们将其摧毁
we will blast a crater in their racial memory so deep
那种震撼效果会令他们
that they won't come within 1,000 klicks of this place ever again.
永远不敢再靠近我们半步
Yeah! Yeah.
说得对，对!
Jake, it's crazy here. It's full mobilization. They're rigging the shuttle as a bomber.
杰克，他们疯了，全体动员 飞船已装上炸弹
They've got these huge pallets of mine explosives.
他们建立了巨大的矿山炸药装载平台
lt's for some kind of shock-and-awe campaign.
正在准备进行一场可怕的战争
Fricking daisy cutters!
这些该死的炸弹
Quaritch has taken over. He's rolling, and there's no stopping him.
库里奇接管了一切 没有人可以阻止他
-When? -0600 tomorrow.
-什么时间? - 明早6点
-Max! Max! - gotta go.
-麦克斯! - 我得走了
We're screwed!
情况不太妙!
And I was hoping for some sort of tactical plan
我希望能速战速决行动
that didn't involve martyrdom.
不需要牺牲
We're going up against gunships with bows and arrows.
我们以弓箭抵御战机
I have 15 clans out there.
我们有15个部落的人马
That's over 2,000 warriors.
超过2千名战士
Now, we know these mountains. We fly them. You fly them. They don't.
我们熟悉山中地有形，我们飞过 你飞过，他们没有
Their instruments won't work up here. Missile tracking won't work.
在这里飞机仪表会失灵，导弹系统会失效
They'll have to fire a line of sight.
他们只能进行目视射击
If they bring the fight to us, then we have the home-field advantage.
他们来进攻，我们有主场之利
You know he's gonna commit that bomber straight to the Tree of Souls.
你知道他们会万炸灵树的
Yeah, I know.
是的
If they get to the Tree of Souls, it's over.
若拱毁灵树，一切就完了
That's their direct line to Eywa, their ancestors.
那是族人跟祖先和艾华的直接联系
It'll destroy them.
那是致命打击
Then I guess we'd better stop him.
所以必须阻止他们
I'm probably just talking to a tree right now.
我可能只是对着树说话
But if you're there, I need to give you a heads-up.
如果你存在，我想告诉你一件事
If Grace is with you, look into her memories.
如果格细丝跟你在一起 请你看看她的记忆
See the world we come from.
看看我们生存的那个世界
There's no green there.
那里一片荒芜
They killed their Mother.
大地之母被摧毁了
And they're gonna do the same here.
他们又想毁掉潘多拉
More Sky People are gonna come.
更多的天空人会来到这里
They're gonna come like a rain that never ends.
像一场下不停的十
Unless we stop them.
除非能阻止他们
Look, you chose me for something.
你看，你在页责中选择了我
I will stand and fight.
我会战斗到底
You know I will.
你知道我会的
But I need a little help here.
不过我需要一点帮助
Our Great Mother does not take sides, Jake.
我们的全能之母不偏不全，杰克
She protects only the balance of life.
她的神圣职责是保护生态平衡
It was worth a try.
我必须试试
Yeah! Yeah! That's what I'm talking about!
对，对，就是这样 !
Yeah! Yeah! That's what I'm talking about, man!
对，就是这样!
This is Group Leader. We are entering the Flux Vortex.
这是队长，我们进入磁旋涡区域
-Switch to manual flight mode. -Copy. Manual flight mode.
- 改换手动飞行模式 - 明白，改换手动飞行模式
This is Papa Dragon.
我是飞龙老爸
I want this mission high and tight. I want to be home for dinner.
任务要求速战速决，我们得赶回去吃晚餐
-Suit Team, go. -All right, ladies, let's bring the pain!
-看你们的了 - 好吧，孩子们，看我们的了
Move, move, move!
快! 快! 快!
Bravo 1-1, move left.
B11，向左移动
Bravo 1-1 moving left. Watch flank.
了明自，向左移动，注意两避
-Watch formation. Keep moving. -Roger that.
- 注意保持队形，前进 - 明白
Charlie 2-1, watch your spacing.
C21，注意距离
Copy that. Over.
了明自，对话完毕
Eyes up. Check that overhead. And watch those thermal scans.
注意，小心头项，注意红外探测器
All call signs, Papa has lead, pushing to target.
全体注意，听我的命令，向目标快速推进
Escorts, stay close on my shuttle.
护航飞机，跟紧我
We are gonna lose some paint in here.
看来小刮小蹦是免不了了
Gun crews, keep your head ona swivel.
射击手要时刻保持警惕
Make no mistake, people, they're out there.
确保万无一失，他们就在附近
All right, people, target in sight. Range, four klicks.
听着，目标就在前面，距离4公里
Valkyrie 1-6, get your payload ready.
瓦尔基里16号，投弹准备
-Copy. Prepare to offload. -Staff Sergeant, stage the weapon.
- 明白，准备投弹 - 上士，准备投弹
Roll it to the ramp! Let's go!
炸弹推到舱口!
Hold!
稳住!
Charlie 2-1, got big movement.
C21，有动静
-Hold position. -Hold up, hold up.
- 停止 - 停止前进
-We got movement out there, 500 meters. -Charlie 2-1, hold position.
- 发现和政情，前方500米处 - C21，停止前进
Sir, ground has movement! Fast approaching.
长官，发现敌人骑兵! 正在快速移动
-Charlie Oscar, Rider section. -Firing line!
- 骑手呼叫 - 准备开火!
Targets closing. Range, 400 meters.
目标向我逼近，距离400米
-Can't you clean it up? -No, sir. It's the Flux.
-图像调清楚些 - 不行，有磁场干扰
Brother, I'm gonna punch a hole. You follow me through.
我先冲开缺口，你们跟我上
All aircraft, weapons free! Weapons free!
全体注意，自主射击，自主射击
Break right. Come around.
快，掉转方向
Light them up!
开火!
Break formation, engage all hostiles.
散开，彻底消灭他们
Yeah! Get some!
打中了!
Scorpions, pursue and destroy.
天蝎号，赶尽杀绝
Jake! Jake! You copy?
杰克，杰克，了上听到没有
We're falling back! We're getting hammered!
我们开始撤退! 我们伤亡惨重!
Copy. Get out of there.
明白，马上离开那里
That's him. Get after him!
他在那儿，给我人筷上去!
Take him out!
干掉他!
Light her up!
打掉她!
Right there!
在那儿 !
You're not the only one with a gun, bitch.
有枪的不只你一个，混球儿
-Keep her in your sights. -Purging. Feeding the leak.
- 给我盯紧她 - 狠狠地打，绝不能放过她
Arming all pods.
装满弹药
That's it!
打得好!
Seze!
施斯 !
Rogue One is hit. I'm going in.
我的飞机中弹，开始返航
Sorry, Jake.
对不起，杰克
Fire.
开火
Tsu'tey! Brother, do you read?
苏泰，听到没有? 兄弟
Rogue One, you copy?
朱迪，上听到没有?
Trudy!
朱迪!
Time to target, two minutes.
距离目标2分外
Valkyrie 1-6, you are cleared and hot.
瓦尔基里16号，可以开始又炸了
Copy, Dragon. We are starting our bomb run.
了明自，老爸，启动投弹程序
-Arm number one! -Number one armed!
-1号解除保险! -1号保险解除!
Ma Jake!
杰克 !
l read you.
收到，请讲
-Neytirif -Seze's dead.
- 奈蒂莉 - 施斯死了
They are very close. They are many.
他们上来了，人很多
Do not attack.
不要攻击
Do you read me, Neytiri?
听到没有，奈蒂莉?
Do not attack!
不要攻击!
Fall back now. Get out of there! That's an order!
撤退，离开那里，这是命令!
Neytirif
奈蒂莉!
got movement, [ got movement.
发现情况，发现情况
Hold position. Something's coming.
停止前进，有动静
Bravo 1-1, l got a big seating. Turn screens over.
C11，发现收情，注意屏幕
-We got movement 200 meters. -Hold your formation.
- 前方200米处发现敌人 - 保持队形
-Be ready. -Watch your flanks.
- 准备好 - 注意两避
Hundred meters and closing fast.
还有一百米，迅速接近
-Fall back! Fall back! -Move! Move! Move!
- 后撤! 后撤! -快! 快! 快!
Fall back! On the run! On the run!
后撤! 快撤! 快撤!
Jake, Eywa has heard you.
杰克，艾华女神听到了
Eywa has heard you!
艾华女神听到了 !
Come on!
冲啊!
Fall back! Move! Move!
后撤! 快! 快!
Sir! All escorts are down or falling back.
长官! 护航飞机全被击落或者逃散
Let's get this done. Valkyrie 1-6, this is Dragon.
只能孤注一掷了 瓦尔基里16号，我是老爸
-Press to target. -Copy. Pressing to target.
- 强攻目标 - 明白，强攻目标
Stand by to drop, 30 seconds.
投弹准备，30秘
On my mark. Two, one, mark.
听我命令2、1，投弹
Drop! Drop! Drop! Go, go, go, go!
投弹! 投弹! 快!
Brace!
坐稳!
It's Sully.
是萨利
-Mask on! -Breach alarm!
- 氧气罩! - 警报响了 !
Come on. Come to papa.
来是，找爸爸来
Give it up, Quaritch!
投降吧，库里奇
It's all over.
该结束了
Nothing's over while I'm breathing.
只要我活着就不会结束
I kind of hoped you'd say that.
我要的就是这句话
Come on!
来吧!
Hey, Sully, how's it feel to betray your own race?
萨利，背叛自己人是什么感觉?
You think you're one of them?
你以为你是他们的人?
Time to wake up.
醒醒吧
Jake?
杰克?
Jake! Ma Jake!
杰克! 我的杰克!
I] See you.
我看到你
The aliens went back to their dying world.
人类返回了他们行将消亡的地球
Only a few were chosen to stay.
只有少数的人被选择留下
The time of great sorrow was ending.
悲惨的时代就要结束了
Toruk Macto was no longer needed.
不再需要终影骑士
Well, 1 guess this is my last video log.
这应该是我最后的视频日记
‘Cause whatever happens tonight, either way, I'm...
因为不论今晚发生什么
I'm not gonna be coming back to this place.
我都不会再回到这里了
Well, I guess I'd better go.
我想我得走了
Yeah, I don't want to be late for my own party.
我不想在聚会上迟到
Yeah, it's my birthday, after all.
今天毕亮是我的生日
This is Jake Sully signing off.
就这样吧，我是杰克萨利，结束了
English - US
Mandarin - Simplified